Nellie Caroll Papers
Nellie Caroll Papers
1923-2001
Caroll, Nellie.
7.3 linear ft.
Papers of the American artist, cartoonist and illustrator documenting her professional and personal life. Original artwork for cartoons, greeting cards, television and costume designs; printed and published material, particularly studio greeting cards; textiles; correspondence; caricatures; memorabilia; and writings.
149713
Biographical History
Nellie Caroll (1923-2005) was a California-based artist known for her studio greeting cards.
Caroll was born as Jean Dobrin on April 3, 1923 in Zillah, Washington. She attended the Mar-Ken School in the Los Angeles area, a school for children in show business, and she also studied at the Art Center School. Caroll moved to New York City and opened an art gallery but later returned to Los Angeles.
Nellie started the Nellie Card Company to produce the studio cards, an emerging type of greeting cards. In the 1950s, Caroll was hired by Box Cards which was headed by Bill Box and Bill Kennedy. Hallmark also used Caroll's greeting card designs. In addition to greeting cards, Caroll worked in commercial art, illustration and in television. Caroll also created several panel cartoons. Her Lady Chatter panel was distributed by the Los Angeles Time Syndicate from 1965 to 1966. Her cartoons and caricatures frequently focused on women.
In 1968 Caroll filed for bankruptcy. She died on May 18, 2005.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Nellie Caroll Papers are arranged in four series and consist of artwork, correspondence, memorabilia (mostly about Caroll's personal life) and writings. The collection documents Caroll's family: particularly her relationship with her only daughter, Amy, who died in 2001 and Caroll's husband.
The Artwork (1956-1998) series consists of Caroll’s creative work and encompasses the variety of genres in which she worked. Included are original drawings, proofs, reproductions and finished products. Caroll's original artwork typically appears on translucent paper. The bulk of the cartoon material is original artwork and proofs for her panel cartoon Lady Chatter distributed by the Los Angeles Times Syndicate from 1965 to 1966. There are smaller amounts of material related to her other cartoons. Caroll's work typically depicted female attitudes (sometimes stereotypical in nature) about life and relationships.
There are also roughs (contained in spiral bound notepads) of children’s books written and illustrated by Caroll in the 1970s, designs, and illustrations for the book Big Al Sports from the Laugh-In television show. Samples of Caroll’s commercial artwork for retail stores and businesses in the Los Angeles area are also included. Greeting card material includes primarily printed studio cards for her own Nellie Card Company, Box Cards, Buzza Cardozo and Hallmark. Worth noting is an inflatable greeting card in the shape of an iron. Caroll's television work includes costume designs for the Laugh In television show and work for Sid and Marty Krofft and Chuck Barris Productions. Examples of Caroll's textiles include designs and finished products for aprons, pillows, clothing and accessories.
Correspondence (1920s-2004) consists primarily of incoming correspondence. Included in the business correspondence are rejection letters for Caroll’s various projects and terms of her agreements with the Los Angeles Times Syndicate and the McNaught Syndicate. There are also letters from Hallmark and a letter regarding a staff position at American Greetings. Of interest is a folder of correspondence with Mattel which includes sample Barbie doll clothing. There is also personal correspondence that was exchanged within Caroll's family, particularly with Caroll’s daughter Amy. The personal correspondence documents Caroll's friendships with actor Jack Larson and musician Michael Franks. Of interest is a cassette tape with a label indicating the recording is of Franks regarding Amy Caroll's death and Larson regarding Ira Gershwin's wife.
Memorabilia (1993-2001) contains a variety of material, much of which relates to Caroll’s family, including her daughter and husband. There are photographs, clippings, bankruptcy records and items reflecting Caroll's interest in mysticism, spirituality, tarot and astrology. Of interest may be a videotape of a documentary in which Caroll appeared.
Writings includes typed stories and also poetry exchanged between Caroll and her husband. Of interest is a history of a particular building's occupants and uses on Sunet Boulevard.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by type of material; within that, alphabetical by name or title. Note that Oversize 6 no longer exists; it contained Les Carroll material, which, along with some material from Oversize 5, was misidentified as being part of this collection. They have been transferred to their own collection, Les Carroll Cartoons.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
Four books have been removed from the collection and transferred to Rare Books for cataloging:
Burn This, a compilation of Box Cards studio cards
Edith Head: the Life and Times of Hollywood's Celebrated Designer
Litter Poems (illustrated by Caroll)
Studio Cards: Funny Greeting Cards and People Who Created Them
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Cartoonists; Caroll, Nellie.; Krofft, Marty, 1937-; Krofft, Sid, 1929-; Chuck Barris Productions.; Lady Chatter.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc., -- United States.; Illustrators -- United States.; Television -- Art direction.; Women artists -- United States.; Women cartoonists -- United States.; Women -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Caricatures.; Cartoons (humorous images); Comics.; Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Children's books.; Greeting cards.; Textiles.; Sketches.; Family papers.; Artists.; Cartoonists.; Illustrators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - Books
    - 500 Pennies Make a Fat Pig, 1973 (Oversize 2)
    - Alphapets, undated; drawings, reproductions (Oversize 2)
    - Arithme Tricks, undated; photocopy of book (Oversize 2)
    - Big Al Sports, circa 1970; drawings (Oversize 3)
    - Book jacket samples, undated (Box 4)
    - Catamania, circa 1970s (Oversize 2)
    - Compact discs of children’s books, 1998; Kodak Photo CDs (Oversize 2)
    - Crazy Critters, undated; photocopy of book (Oversize 2)
    - Hands Are For Waving Hi, by Francesca Riviere, illustrated by Caroll, 1975 (Oversize 2)
    - Litter Poems by Henry Gibson, circa 1970s; drawings (Oversize 3)
    - Money Talks, 1970 (Oversize 2)
    - My Name is Amy Caroll…, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Our Friends the Toes written by Francesca Riviere, illustrated by Caroll, 1970 (Oversize 2)
    - Rubber animal stamps, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Seven Bad Kids and How They Got Better, 1979 (Oversize 2)
    - To Be or Not Two Bee, 1974 (Oversize 2)
    - What’s in a Name, undated (Oversize 2)
  - Cartoons
    - Ding - a - Ling, undated; drawings (Box 4)
    - Dr. Shrinker, undated; drawings and proofs (Box 4)
    - The Female Dilemma, undated (Box 4)
    - His and Hers, 1969; correspondence, contract, proofs (Box 4)
    - His and Hers, 1969; proofs (Oversize 1)
    - Lady Chatter, 1965-1966; 2 folders; proofs (Box 4)
    - Lady Chatter, 1965-1966; 2 folders; proofs (Oversize 3)
    - Lady Chatter, 1965 or 1966; proofs (Oversize 5)
    - Lady Chatter, 1965-1966; drawings (Oversize 7)
    - Lady Chatter, 1965-1966; publicity (Box 4)
  - Commercial
    - Carnival of Puppets / D’Jon Puppets, undated; printed material (Box 4)
    - C.D. Originals / Tracy Dawson Show Rooms, undated; printed material (Box 4)
    - C.H. Baker shoes, undated; drawings (Oversize 1)
    - Phelps- Wilger’s Etcetera Shop, undated (Oversize 3)
    - Standard Brand Shoes, undated; drawings (Oversize 3)
    - Stationary, undated (Box 5)
    - Sterling Automotive service, undated; printed material (Oversize 3)
    - Village Vendors, undated; shopping bags and clipping (Box 4)
  - Greeting Cards
    - Advertising post cards, undated (Box 1)
    - Artwork, undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Christmas drawings, undated (Box 5)
    - Drawings, circa 1950s-1960s; 4 folders (Oversize 1)
    - Blow Up Greeting Card, 1969; inflatable iron (Box 1)
    - Box Cards catalog, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Box Cards and Buzza Cardozo oversize greeting cards, 1961-1962; undated (Box 1)
    - Buzza Cardozo, undated; greeting cards (Box 1)
    - Hallmark, 1960s; greeting cards (Box 1)
    - Box Cards Negatives, 1956; greeting cards (Box 2)
    - Box Cards Christmas, 1959; greeting cards (Box 2)
    - Box Cards, 1960-1962; greeting cards (Box 2)
    - Box Cards, 1959-1962; greeting cards (Box 2)
    - Box Cards, undated; greeting cards (Box 2)
    - Box Cards, 1959; 1961; greeting cards (Box 2)
    - Box Cards, 1956-1957; 1959; greeting cards (Box 2)
    - Box Cards styled by Nellie, 1955-1956; greeting cards (Box 2)
    - Box Cards styled by Nellie, undated; greeting cards (Box 2)
    - Nellie Card Company, 1957; greeting cards (Box 1)
    - Nellie Card Company catalog and samples, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Reed Starline, undated; greeting cards (Box 2)
    - "Retro" Nellie Card Company samples and mockups, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Television
    - Chuck Barris Productions, 1968-1969; clippings, correspondence, drawings (Box 4)
    - Chuck Barris Productions, 1960s; artwork, printed material; 2 folders (Oversize 3)
    - George Schlatter- Ed Friendly Productions, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Laugh-In costume designs, 1968 (Oversize 8)
    - Sid and Marty Krofft, 1969; undated; printed material (Oversize 3)
    - Sid and Marty Krofft Circus 70, 1970; roughs (Oversize 3)
    - Turn On, 1969; clippings (Box 4)
    - Turn On, circa 1969; roughs (Oversize 1)
  - Textiles
    - Apron designs, undated (Box 5)
    - Aprons, undated; canvas (Oversize 4)
    - Last Year in Temkin costume designs, undated (Box 5)
    - Men's clothing designs, undated; photocopies (Box 5)
    - Satin pillows, undated; photos, printed material (Box 5)
    - Satin pillows, undated; sample (Oversize 4)
    - Shirt with floral design, undated (Oversize 4)
    - T-shirt designs, undated (Box 5)
    - Tote bags, undated; canvas; 4 items (Oversize 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Alphabet letters preschool educational toy design, 1973 (Oversize 2)
    - Art Director's Therapy Block, undated (Oversize 3)
    - Caricatures of Caroll and Jack Larson by Bachardy, 1960s; reproductions (Oversize 3)
    - Drawings, reproductions, slides, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Off Color, undated; drawings (nudes) (Oversize 1)
    - Record Album covers, 1959; undated (Oversize 3)
    - Miscellaneous, undated; drawings, proofs (Oversize 1)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1960s; undated; 2 folders; drawings, mock ups; includes "Dames At Sea" (Oversize 3)
- Correspondence
  - A-Z, 1943; 1954-1969; incoming (Box 3)
  - Bernstein, Amy and Lou, 1993-1994; 1998 (Box 3)
  - Caroll, Amy, 1948; 1957,; 1986,; 1991,; 1993-1994,; 1999,; undated; includes birth registration, childhood drawings and writings (Box 3)
  - Family letters, 1920s-1930s; undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Franks, Michael and Claudia, 1994; 2000,; undated; includes cassette tape of Michael and Nellie on phone about death of Nellie’s daughter and Jack Larson about Ira Gershwin's wife (Box 3)
  - Larson, Jack, 1996-2000 (Box 3)
  - Letters and ideas, 1991-1992; 1994-1995,; 1997-1999,; undated (Box 3)
  - Mattel, 1968; includes Barbie clothes and designs (Box 3)
  - Outgoing, 1967-1968; 1999,; 2004,; undated (Box 3)
  - Peterman, J., 1998 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1952; 1955; 1992,; 1997,; 2000,; undated (Box 4)
- Memorabilia
  - Astrological chart prepared by Amy Caroll, 1998; with photo (Box 4)
  - Augusta Dobrin’s story, undated (Box 4)
  - Bernstein, Amy and Lou, 1998-1999; photos and writings (Box 5)
  - Biographical material, 1937; 1964,; undated; 2 folders; photos, clippings, bankruptcy (Box 5)
  - Books
    - Big Al's Sport Scene, 1970; 2 copies; one copy with letter (photocopy) and one inscribed to Martin from Nellie with love (Box 6)
    - Books on religion, mysticism, Hermeticism, Kabbalah, photocopies of title pages and covers; Original books have been discarded. (Box 6)
    - Inscribed to Caroll, 6 items; Aleister Crowley, Buddhism, Hermeticism and works by Israel Regardie (Box 6)
    - Litter Poems by Henry Gibson, circa 1969; with two letters (Box 6)
  - Caroll, Amy, 1999; Angelic Tarot guide (Box 5)
  - Caroll, Amy, 2001; undated; resume and photos (Box 4)
  - Caroll, Amy, 1999; tarot cards (Box 6)
  - Clippings and printed material, 1955-1960; 1964,; 1966,; 1968,; 1970; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Compact discs from Michael Franks, 1995; 1999 (Box 5)
  - Dame Edna photograph, undated (Box 4)
  - Dobrin store advertising plaques, undated (Oversize 4)
  - Edward James: Builder of Dreams- a brief appearance by Nellie and husband, undated; videotape (Box 5)
  - Family documents, 1923; 1926,; 1947,; 1980,; 1985,; 1998,; undated (Box 4)
    some items include:
    labeled family photograph
    Mr. and Mrs. Joseph Rosenthal 50th wedding anniversary menu
    Funeral records, death certificate, and living will for family members
    Caroll's Baby book
    Letters from Caroll's first husband
  - Martir, Agustin Ramos, 1970-1971; 1979,; 1985,; 1989 (Box 4)
  - Martir, Agustin Ramos, undated; slides (Box 5)
  - Mother’s pregnancy meditation, 1923 (Oversize 4)
  - My Mother’s Life, undated (Box 4)
  - Poster for "Cherry, Larry, Sandy, Doris, Jean, Paul" by Jack Larson, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Tarot cards, undated; color photos (Box 6)
- Writings
  - B-G, 2000; undated (Box 5)
    The Ball of Gold
    Everybody Has One
    The Fixer Upper
    For Lease
    Get Out of Town
    The Golden Plated Years
  - H-S, 1993; undated (Box 5)
    History of the Block 8800 W. Sunset Boulevard
    Images of Love
    The Rose of India
    The Sinking Sands
  - Poetry, 1964; 1998-1999,; undated; poems and photos with husband (Box 5)